No! No! No!
不 不
Madam, you are unwell.
夫人 你气色不太好呀
She needs a hot dinner, brother Chimney.
她需要一顿热腾腾的晚餐 钱宁兄弟
I saw her first, brother Joliffe.
是我先看到她的 若利夫兄弟
Do not tire yourself, sir.
别累着了 先生
We travel before first peep of day.
明天天亮前我们就要出发
Well, Madam...what say you?
怎样 夫人 意下如何?
What has been your business in Oxford, sir?
你在牛津做什么买卖 先生
To sell corn, my dear.
我卖粮食的 亲爱的
You're a farmer?
你是一位农夫?
I sell corn...which is a mite easier than growing the stuff.
我只卖粮食 这比种粮食要稍微容易一点
No armies trample over my profits.
不会有军队践踏我的产业
And the King's court must still be fed.
而王宫也照样需要吃饭
Shall I call the boy?
要叫人给你加酒吗?
You want me drunk, madam?
你想灌醉我 夫人
I knew it were so!
我就知道
Such a bonny lady, such a fine face,
如此标致的女子 如此俊俏的脸蛋
but we must all eat, must we not?!
但我们也都需要吃饭 是吧
In times as these, a man must make hard bargains...
如今这世道 男人都要唯利是图
and a woman must sell what a man will buy.
而女人就得听从男人的价码
Shall I call the boy?
我去叫酒童吧
No, dear Madam... for I am lusty enough.
不 亲爱的夫人 我已经够有兴致了
Come, come.
来吧 来吧
You've had your pay.
你已经得到报酬了
Come, let me help you.
来吧 我来帮你
Sir, I beg of you.
先生 我求你了
Oh, no, no, no,
哦 不 不
we'll have no tears.
我们不哭
For we are jolly here.
我们要来快活快活
Now off with the rest, open your pretty legs and all is done.
剩下的呢 你只要把双脚张开就可以了
Sir, I think you have a wife somewhere.
先生 我想你应该有家室了吧
I beg you think.
我求您想想清楚
Madam. No more of this.
夫人 别再说这些了
Will you run me through?
你会捅死我吗
I think you will not.
我猜你不会
Madam, will you get on your back?
夫人 请你仰面躺下
Well, then I see you need another smack.
看来你还需要一巴掌
Oh, God!
哦 上帝
Do not call for God, sir.
请不要喊上帝 先生
He's turned his face from us both.
他已把你我都抛弃了
The country starves, Thomas.
全国都在闹饥荒 托马斯
But Oliver,there is food enough for those with coin to pay for it.
但奥利弗 可那些有钱人可以花钱买到粮食
Parliament men sign themselves passes
议会的议员们给自己签署过关文书
through my lines and sell corn to our enemies in Oxford.
到牛津把粮食卖给我们的敌人
The country looks to the Army for justice.
国家需要由军队来主持公道
The country looks for order.
国家需要的是秩序
They want their King back in his place.
他们想让国王重掌政权
They want their world safe again.
他们想要国家回复安定
You know my mind on that.
这一点你知道我心里所想
What is yours?
你是怎么想的
We are as one, and ever will be.
你我同心共志 托马斯 一直都将是
But Charles Stuart will ever be King.
但查尔斯-斯图亚特将一直会是国王
How can Charles Stuart be King and the world be safe?
可要是让斯图亚特当国王 这世界如何能得到安宁
God will provide us the answer.
上帝会给我们答案的
The starving copyholder nor the unpaid soldier will not wait
可饥饿的土地主和无酬士兵可等不及天空中
for the firmament to split
裂开一条缝
and shine God's beam on us, Oliver!
上帝的光芒从中透出普照你我 奥利佛
We must make our own light shine.
我们要创造自己的光芒
On the King, on the parliament of thieves and on property.
照射到国王 照射到匪徒议会 还有产业
Property?
产业?
Land should be a common treasury.
土地必须成为共有财产
Let every man have a share of it
让每个人都拥有自己的土地
and there'll be no starving. Men will feed themselves.
这样就不会有饥饿了 人们可以自给自足
Where's that land to come from?
土地从哪里来呢 托马斯
It must be taken from those who have too much.
要从那些拥有太多土地的人手里拿
You would have us turn to robbery then?
你是要把我们变成强盗了
Farewell, Colonel.
再见 上校
Farewell, General.
再见 将军
Why did these members of parliament...
为什么这些议会议员
induce us to fight in the name of freedom...
诱导我们为了自由而战
only that we might now endure their greed
可现在我们要么忍受他们的贪婪
or suffer their prisons?
要么被关到牢里
I tell ya, this is no freedom except for them!
这个国家没有自由 除了他们自己
And where sat they while we fought for their profits?
在我们为他们的利益作战时 他们在哪里
At home counting their money.
他们在家里数钱呢
I tell ya, we are robbed once more.
我跟你们说 我们再一次地遭受着剥削
Not by King alone this time, but by parliament as well!
这一次不单是国王 还包括议会
Voice of the people, John.
你是人民的呼声 约翰
Let them! Let them come!
让他们过来 让他们来吧
Let them come.
让他们来吧
Comrades!
朋友们
We fought side by side for liberty!
我们肩并肩地为自由而战
What did you fight for all that time?
而你们是为何而战?
To be the dogs that parliament would throw me to?
是要成为议会养着来咬我的狗吗
Incarcerate me, sirs, I am a free born man!
囚禁我吧 我是生来自由的人
Try again.
再试一次
Sexby. I was told you were dead at Kineton fight.
塞斯比 我听说你战死在金内顿了
Death indeed sought me out. Like a lover.
死亡确实一直在追随着我 就像个爱人
But yet I live.
不过我还活着
I thank you.
多亏你
God in heaven...
至高无上的上帝呀
help me, please!
救救我吧
You are much changed, my Lady.
你改变了很多 夫人
You are not, I see.
而你没变 我看得出
Where to?
去哪里
Tonight I know not.
今晚 我不知道
Tomorrow, London. There to make a new beginning.
明天要到伦敦 寻找新的生活
It'll be dark soon.
天很快就要黑了
They'll not have gone far.
他们肯定还没跑远
There's rabbit.
这里有只野兔
How did your husband die?
你丈夫是怎么死的?
He died because I was not tame.
他是因为我的不驯而死的
The world would have you tame.
这个世界会让你驯服的      是啊
Then the world is full of fools.
那这个世界上的人就都是愚蠢之徒
How came you by those clothes?
你这些衣装是从何而来的?
A man gave them to me.
一名男子送给我的
I killed a man.
我杀了个人
Nothing remains of who I was.
我已非昔日的我了
At Axholme, where I was born, men came to drain the fens
在我出生之地阿克斯霍姆 早年人们掘渠排水
and when the water flowed away, they found men...
当洪水退去 他们发现了一些尸体
..buried in the peat. Like this.
埋在於泥中 就像这样
Hands tied to legs. Holes here...
手脚被绑在一起 这里都有一个洞
Stones or hammers...
用石头或是锤子敲的
And a black god...
还有一个黑色的神像
..made in wood, kept perfect in the ground.
用木头做的 完整地埋在地下
Where is that god now, I wonder?
我不知那个神现在哪里
If all his worshippers are buried in the ground with him,
如果他所有的信徒都和他一起被埋葬了
is he still a god then?
那他还算是个神吗?
If a King runs away from his country,
一个国王如果弃国出逃
is he still a King then?
那他还算个国王吗?
He left England?
他离开英格兰了?
He gave himself to the Scots,
他逃到苏格兰人那里
hoping for a new Army, they say.
希望他们派出一支援兵
But the Scots know a bargain.
但苏格兰人很会做买卖
They've sold him to the parliament.
他们把他卖给了议会
How can you laugh?
你如何还能笑得出来
I thought Charles Stuart King, God and Father once.
我曾经把查尔斯-斯图亚特 当成国王 上帝和父亲
Madam.
夫人
We enter the world alone and in blood
我们在鲜血中独自降临在这世上
and leave the same way.
我们也将同样地离开
What happens in between means little.
在这之间发生的事毫无意义
I will be no man's whore.
我不会随便委身于人的
Do nothing but sit by the fire
坐到火堆边不要动
and look like a feast.
装得柔弱些
Look what I found on the road to London.
看看我在去伦敦的路上看到了什么
A whore in a dead man's shirt.
一个穿着死人衣裳的婊子
Take his clothes from her.
把她的衣服剥掉
You will pay with your own life, for that of my friend.
你要用你的命来还我朋友的命
But first...
不过首先呢
Lay her down.
把她放倒
Or would you rather I kill him?
或者你要我来杀他?
You're the devil, sir.
你是个魔鬼 先生
And you, madam, the devil's whore.
而夫人你 你是魔鬼的荡妇
Enough, enough killing.
够了 别再杀人了
The devil's whore gives the orders.
由魔鬼的荡妇发号施令
What times we live in.
这是什么世道
Go home, sir, to your wife.
回家吧 先生 回到你妻子身边
Your money will go to the poor whose taxes you live on.
你的钱将被发放给缴税养你的穷人
A whore and a Leveller too,
荡妇兼平等派
well may you prosper as Master Lilburne does.
那祝你像里尔本先生一样成功
Walled up in stone.
被关在石墙里
By whose order?
谁下的令?
By the parliament.
议会
We will meet again, madam.
后会有期 夫人
"Free Born" John walled up again.
"自由人"约翰又被关起来了
His wife will need money.
他妻子一定很缺钱
Then I see you have found another God to worship.
这么说您如今崇拜一位新神了
The Holy Trinity - truth, liberty and justice.
圣三位一体 真理 自由与正义
And what is that but more blood?
可除了要流更多的血 还有什么呢?
And tell me, when all the blood is spilled,
告诉我 等到该洒的鲜血洒尽
what then?
然后呢?
Who will be master and who will be slave?
谁会是主人 谁又会是奴隶?
Will I be King?
我会当国王吗?
Will my lady work in the fields?
夫人您会下地干活吗?
There is a madness in you that feeds on the times, Sexby.
你有一种疯病 以世事变迁为食 塞斯比
Do not laugh at me, sir.
不要取笑我 先生
Between blood of birth and blood of death there is life.
在生与死的血污之间还有生活
And this fight is now my life.
眼下 这场斗争就是我的生活
What is yours?
你的是什么?
To laugh at hope?
嘲笑希望?
To live and die alone?
孤独地生老病死?
Nay.
不
I would not have that life.
我不想过那种生活
Turn your back.
转过身去
I wish to dress in my skirts again.
我想重新换上女装
Must you?
您一定要吗?
Must I what, sir?
一定要什么 先生?
Put on your clothes?
穿上衣服?
I mean only to swim.
我只想游个泳
Swim naked with me, madam...
与我一起裸泳吧 夫人
..And we will both take gold to Honest John.
然后我们一起去送钱给正直的约翰
He can have my share too.
我那份也给他
All I ask is that you swim with me.
我只求您与我一起裸泳
Stand off.
站远些
Will you not swim, Sexby?
你不游吗 塞斯比?
I never could swim.
我从来不会游
From a friend in the Parliament you say?
你说是议会里一位朋友送的?
Indeed.
没错
I knew not I had a friend in the Parliament.
我不知道我在议会还有朋友呢
John, 28 pounds.
约翰 28磅
Enough to buy a new printing press.
够买台新印刷机了
And some clothes for the children.
还有孩子们的新衣服
Aye, a new press.
遵命 新印刷机
I thought the fight had lost you, Edward.
我以为你远离战场了 爱德华
No, John.
不 约翰
The fight will never lose me again.
我再也不会远离战场了
My sword is drawn.
我的剑已出鞘了
This is the fight now.
现在的战斗在这里了
Words?
文章?
Read.
念念
You hold his life in your hands.
你手中握着他的性命
Both sides will call it treason.
两方面都会管这叫叛国
"Parliament to be forcibly adjourned
"将议会强制休会"
"and a new one elected by all men of good faith,
"新议会由所有诚实公民共同选举"
"not only those with property."
"而非少数有产者"
The levelling up of men cannot begin until this is accomplished.
没有这一步 不可能将世人拉平
"That new Parliament to have Charles Stuart...
"由新议会将查尔斯·斯图亚特..."
"..Arrested."
"逮捕"
"And tried as a man of blood..."
"以杀人罪审判"
Who will do the levelling up?
那谁来实现平等呢?
The army, Edward. Where you should be still.
军队 爱德华 你也应该在那里
There is no other engine to drive the world's turning but the army.
世界前进的动力莫强于军队
Will you take these pages out?
你能把这些文件带出去吗?
They must find their way to a press.
必须想办法找人付印才行
I am searched.
我会被搜身
Even my skirts.
裙底也不放过
The dogs.
那帮走狗
Where is the press?
在哪付印?
At your house, madam,
在您家 夫人
with Thomas Rainsborough.
托马斯·恩巴勒那里
We must search you, sir. On my master's orders.
我们必须搜你的身 先生 主子有令
And who is your master?
你们的主子是谁?
That you need not know.
这你不用管
Madam?
夫人?
Go, madam!
快走 夫人!
Where is she?
她在哪?
This was my mother's chapel.
这是我母亲的礼拜堂
My, er, soldiers are godly men.
我的士兵们都是好基督徒
They will not tolerate idolatry.
他们不能容忍偶像崇拜(天主教)
My mother worshipped her God through painted clay.
我母亲透过这金装泥偶礼拜着她的上帝
I am glad to see you safe and well, madam.
您平安无事真让人欣慰 夫人
These two years I tried for news of you many times.
过去两年我到处打听您的消息
I feared you were sick.
我担心您是病了
Or worse.
或者更糟
I was never more alive.
我从没有这么有活力过
From Honest John.
正直的约翰给你的
We are in your debt.
我们欠您一次情
This house is given to the army for a while.
这幢房子要被军队征用一阵
Though I must make free with a part of it,
尽管我必须擅自处置其中一部分
the rest is yours.
剩下的还是您的
How fares Joshua?
约书亚过得怎样?
Madam?
夫人?
God sent these floods to trap you.
"上帝遣来洪水将你们陷入困境"
Now he sends you Rainsborough and Cromwell,
"现在又派来雷恩巴勒和克伦威尔"
like Joshua and Gideon
"就像约书亚和基甸"
to drown you in fire and blood.
"用血与火湮灭你们"
You broke a King's heart.
你们打碎了国王的心
And killed some innocents too, madam.
也杀了些无辜的人 夫人
My hands are stained in blood.
我的手已经沾了血
A Joshua indeed.
真成约书亚了
I've heard that all of your family is in the New World, Colonel.
我听说您的家人都去新大陆了 上校
My mother, my brother, and my sisters.
我母亲 我弟弟 还有我的姐妹们
But not your wife then?
可您的夫人不在?
I will have no wife until this quarrel be over.
这场纷争不平息 我便不娶妻
And how would you settle the quarrel?
您要怎么平息这纷争呢?
By making England a republic.
将英格兰变成共和国
And if England wants Charles Stuart on his throne again?
要是英格兰想要查尔斯·斯图亚特复位呢
Then I will leave England to its King
那我就将英格兰留给它的国王
and go to Massachusetts.
搬去麻萨诸塞
And find me a wife there.
在那里找一位妻子
And what shall she be, Colonel?
要找怎样的人呢 上校?
Such a one as lives and worships in freedom.
找一位生而自由 信仰自由的
One that knows how to truly love a man and be loved.
懂得如何真正爱一个男人 并且被爱
Oh, and beautiful.
对了 还要美丽
None such in England then?
英格兰就没有吗?
No, I would not have an English wife, madam.
不 我不会娶英国妻子 夫人
Not a painted child that knows nothing
我不要那种懵懵懂懂的洋娃娃
but a thousand years of privilege
脑子里满是一千年的特权
and calls it "breeding" or "manners".
还管那叫"血统"或"礼教"
Calls submission "duty"
管顺从叫"义务"
and lives only to please a man and pass on his property to his sons.
一心只会侍奉男人 给他传宗接代
I will a have a free spirit, madam.
我要找一个自由的灵魂 夫人
All this and beautiful too.
还要加上美貌 先生
I fear you will not find this paragon.
这么理想的人难找呢
I need not find her.
我不必去找她
For I believe she will find me.
我相信她自会找到我
Will you not speak?
您不说话吗?
Might you not hear a thousand years of privilege in my voice?
您不怕听到我声音中一千年的特权吗?
Perhaps a hundred or two.
也许有一两百年吧
General Cromwell wishes to see you.
克伦威尔将军召见你
How is dear John?
亲爱的约翰还好吗?
Well, General, when I saw him.
将军 我见到他时还好
For a man with rats for bedfellows.
就一个终日与老鼠为伴的人来说
He is there by order of Parliament. I cannot pluck him out.
是议会下令关押他的 我不能赦他出来
You plucked me out.
您能赦我出来
You fought bravely by my side at Kineton and at Marston.
你在金内顿和马斯顿英勇地与我并肩作战
As did Honest John.
正直的约翰也是
And at Naseby thereafter.
还有后来在内斯比
Where Charles Stuart lost his throne, did he not?
把查尔斯·斯图亚特赶下了王座 不是吗?
He lost his power, Edward.
他只是失势了 爱德华
But he is King still
可他还是国王
and whoever has him has our destiny in his grip.
谁掌握他 就掌握了我们的命运
The Scotch have sold him to Parliament,
苏格兰人把他出卖给了议会
and Parliament have him sitting in Northamptonshire.
议会把他安置在北安普敦
And if the army were to seize him,
如果我们的军队抓住他
the army would hold sway.
势力就会大增
Then pluck him out of Northamptonshire, General.
那就把他揪出北安普敦 将军
That I may not do.
这我办不到
There is a woman in Oxfordshire.
牛津郡有个女人
Her true name is not known to God-fearing men.
她的真名不为正派人所知
She is known as the Devil's Whore.
她号称魔鬼的妓女
Upon my life, General, this woman is the epitome of wickedness.
我以性命发誓 将军 这女人就是邪恶的化身
Truly, Master Joliffe?
真的 若利夫先生?
What form does this wickedness take?
邪恶以何种方式显形呢?
Lechery, sir.
淫欲 先生
She consorts with men.
她人尽可夫
And what, I pray you, should the army do about that?
我问你 军队又该拿这怎么办?
She is sent from the devil!
她是魔鬼派来的
I must confess, sir.
我必须坦白 先生
Confess?
坦白?
Aye, confess.
对 坦白
I don't want to be silent.
我不喜欢闷不作声
Her licentiousness has a purpose, sir.
她如此放荡成性是有企图的 先生
That purpose is robbery and murder.
这企图便是打劫 谋杀
She...
她...
uses her...
利用她的...
face...
脸蛋...
To trap men.
俘获男人
Well...
嗯...
Wickedness indeed.
确实邪恶啊
The Parliament require you to make a troop available to me
议会要您派一队人马给我
to search out and take this woman.
去抓捕这个女人
My America.
我的美洲
My Newfoundland.
我的新大陆
Edward.
爱德华
Still not dead, then?
还没死呢?
No, my Lady, it seems I must live.
没有 夫人 看来我命不该绝
I bring a message from the General, sir.
我从将军那里捎来了消息 先生
I'll leave you.
我先走吧
No, never. Stay and listen.
不 不要 呆在这听着
He has eyes everywhere.
他的眼线到处都是
I believe not a one of us moves his bowels without Oliver senses it.
相信我们这些人拉泡屎 奥利佛都一清二楚
Craving your pardon, my Lady.
恳请您原谅 夫人
Given.
没关系
He wants the King taken and delivered to the Army
他希望把国王逮捕 送到军中
but he would not give the order.
但却不肯亲自下命令
Aye.
没错
He would rather I did it.
他宁可我来做这些
Whoever does it, risks the wrath of the Parliament.
无论谁开口 都会面临议会的谴责报复
And yet it should be done.
而这件事非办不可
It shall be done, then.
那就这么办吧
Think no more on it.
您不必操心了
I will risk all in the cause.
我来承担一切风险
Fear not, they will not harm me.
别担心 他们不会伤害我
The country would fall to utter ruin without me.
没有我这国家就彻底毁掉了
Your business?
有何贵干?
Sire. We have come to take you into safe-keeping.
陛下 我们要带您去一个安全的地方
On whose authority do you come to take away a King?
谁授权你带走一位国王?
It is a very good authority.
相当有力的授权
Oliver will never strike him down.
奥利佛绝不会罢黜他
He would not be remembered as the man who threw over the King.
他不愿作为打倒国王的人留名青史
Deep down,
内心深处
Oliver believes in the good old frame of government.
奥利佛相信那个良好古老的政权体制
The cloth that went before cut to a different style?
旧瓶装新酒?
Authority where it was, rank where it was, land where it was.
权力依旧 等级依旧 国土依旧
And the women sent home again to be silent wives
女人们被送回家依旧做那个无言的贤妻
in harness to their husbands.
作丈夫的附属
In harness to property.
作产业的附属
There are two roads to the future, Thomas.
未来有两条岔路 托马斯
The Leveller regiments will follow yours.
平等派将士会追随你那条
Then what will Oliver do?
到时候奥利佛怎么办?
And what will Thomas Rainsborough do if the road is blocked?
而如果此路不通 托马斯·雷恩巴勒又会怎么做?
I will become an American.
我会成为美洲人
Like my wife.
就像我妻子
You swore you had no wife, sir.
您发誓说没有娶妻的 先生
Oh, I mean to have one.
哦 我现在打算娶一个
If she will have me.
如果她愿意的话
Colonel!
上校
Stay.
呆着别动
I will return for my answer.
我待会儿回来要我的答案
Colonel, I heard not your question.
上校 我没听到你的问题
Will you be my wife?
你愿意做我的妻子吗?
Colonel! Parliament men!
上校 议会来人了
Well?
怎样?
Come and find your answer when duty allows.
等你忙完正事再来找答案吧
This need not concern you, Colonel,
您不必操心 上校
except your garrison will need to know of
只不过要通知您的卫队
our presence in your area.
我们会在您的管区行动
You bring a troop of horse to seek a woman who stole your purse?
你带领一队人马就为了找一个偷你钱袋的女人?
Read further, sir. She murdered my dear friend.
往下读 先生 她杀了我的好友
Though, again, sir, it need not concern you.
还是那句话 先生 您不必担心
It concerns me that the Parliament thinks the Army
我当然担心 议会认为军队
has no more pressing task to perform
无正事可干
than to indulge the grudges of wealthy men who
要去给那些让别人流血牺牲
stayed at home growing their bellies while others bled to death.
自己在家享清福的有钱人看家护院
My Lady Angelica Fanshawe.
安吉丽卡·范肖夫人
The mistress of this house.
这里的女主人
Ah, my Lady Fanshawe.
啊 范肖夫人
Master Joliffe sits in the Parliament
若利夫先生位居议会
tending the nation's wounds.
关照民众疾苦
He is leaving.
他正要走
A delight to meet you, madam.
很荣幸认识您 夫人
And yet, I swear I have looked upon your face before.
不过 我发誓我以前见过您
At court, perhaps?
也许是在王宫?
Of course. In the court.
当然 是在王宫
I never could forget such a face.
我不会忘记这样的面孔
And I never will.
永远不会
Farewell, Madam.
再会 夫人
Colonel.
上校
Nothing will go well till these leeches are purged.
这些寄生虫不除 国无宁日
What was his business?
他来做什么?
To persecute some whore. He means to have her hanged.
找个荡妇的麻烦 他一心想绞死她
My answer, Madam?
我的答案 夫人?
Do you see him?
你看见他了吗?
See who?
看见谁?
You do not see him?!
你没看见?
I cannot marry you.
我不能嫁给你
There is no future. There is only the past.
我们没有将来 只有过去
Purge of Parliament?
议会大清洗?
Some thrown out, some kept in.
有人被踢出去 有人被留下来
No, I cannot support it.
不 我不支持
They are bloodsuckers.
他们都是些吸血鬼
One sweep of the sword and they are gone. We begin anew.
一剑斩断他们 我们重获新生
Ah. A new election?
啊 新的选举?
No. We know who the godly men are,
不 我们知道谁是虔诚的
the men who want the best for England. Let them remain.
谁会效忠英格兰 留下他们
No election?
没有选举?
No.
没有
Why no election?
为什么没有选举?
John, the country is half-ruined.
约翰 这个国家已经元气大伤
There is famine in the north and west.
西北部正闹饥荒
Corrupt monopolies flourish.
腐败垄断肆意横行
We must force Parliament to reform.
我们必须胁迫议会改革
We need the support of Honest John Lilburne.
我们需要正直的约翰·李尔本的支持
In God's name, John,
看在上帝份上 约翰
we want to purge the men whose warrant keeps you rotting here!
我们要清扫的是下令让你在这烂掉的人
Why no election?
为什么不选举?
Because the country will vote for the King's men!
因为国民会选择国王的人
And you will turn to dust in this rat-infested hole
而你将会在这老鼠窝里化为尘土
and your wife and children will starve in a gutter!
你的妻小则会饿死在街边的臭水沟中
But I mistake, of course,
不过我错了 当然
for in truth, there is no more comfortable
事实是这世上最让
place on earth for John Lilburne than a prison cell!
约翰·李尔本自在的地方 莫过于监狱了
Where he is spared the trouble of considering
藏在这里 他就不用考虑
the full-grown problems of governance
政府中已然根深蒂固的问题
and not the unborn children of liberty and truth.
而非自由和真理孕育中的孩子
Which will lie forever in the womb if we cannot make a world
它们可能永远躺在子宫之中 如果我们无法打造一个
into which they may be brought!
令其安身的世界
Comfortable?
自在?
Think, John, a purged Parliament
想一想 约翰 一个净化的议会
and a law quickly passed by which no man will have an income
法律很快就能同意不许任何人收入
above 2,000 a year, not even Earls and Dukes.
一年超过2000块 伯爵公爵都包括在内
By what authority would a law such as that be brought in?
凭什么提出这样的法律?
By this authority.
就凭这个
For there is none now else in England, I think you know.
眼下英格兰只有这个算数 你应该清楚
Sir. Within half a day of your departure,
先生 您走后大约半天
Mistress Fanshawe was arrested.
范肖夫人被捕了
She's charged with robbery and murder.
她被控抢劫和谋杀
They will hang me!
他们要绞死我
Lies cannot hang you.
谎言不会绞死你
This was done to attack me, why else?
这是冲我来的 还会是什么?
Thomas, a word.
托马斯 借一步说话
You must not tell him.
你一定不能告诉他
I killed a thief.
我杀死了一个贼
Will he not understand?
他不会理解吗?
No, he will not. He is Thomas Rainsborough,
不 他不会 他是托马斯·雷恩巴勒
not Edward Sexby.
不是爱德华·塞斯比
Then he will hear me condemned in court.
那他会听到我被法庭定罪了
Elizabeth will stay with you.
伊丽莎白会留下陪你
Let me pay a visit to Master Joliffe.
让我去拜访一下若利夫先生
Let me ask him in front of his wife and daughter,
让我当着他妻女的面质问他
how he came to meet this Oxford whore.
他是如何认识这位牛津荡妇的
Let him tell his lies, Edward, the truth will out.
让他说他的谎言吧 爱德华 事实会自己站出来的
Angelica, you wanted to speak?
安吉丽卡 你想说什么?
No.
没有
Mistress Fanshawe, the charges against you are as follows -
范肖夫人 你被指控如下罪行
In the year of our Lord, 1646, you did most cruelly murder
我主纪年1646年 你残忍地杀害了
the corn merchant, Master Chimney.
粮食商人钱宁先生
And that with diverse others in Wytham Woods,
而后伙同他人在威萨姆森林
you did attack and rob Master Joliffe.
袭击并抢劫了若利夫先生
And that you are the notorious felon known as, The Devil's Whore.
加之你还是臭名昭著的魔鬼的荡妇
What is your answer to these charges?
你对此审判有何异议?
That I am no whore...
我不是荡妇...
Liar! Whore!
骗子 荡妇
Hang her!        ..And never was!
绞死她      ..从来不是
If your father continues with this case,
如果你父亲仍不对这案子罢休
your head will follow your hair.
你的人头便会随你的头发落下
We will proceed to the evidence.
下面审查呈堂证供
Master Joliffe...
若利夫先生
Master Joliffe, will you come forward and give your account?
若利夫先生 请你上前来陈词
I...mistook.
我...认错人了
This is not the woman who robbed me.
这不是抢劫我的妇人
That woman was a whore I used many times in Oxford.
那妇人乃是我在牛津光顾过很多次的婊子
All this I swear...on the blood of Christ.
我以基督的血起誓
Release the prisoner.
释放犯人
I ask your forgiveness.
我恳求你的宽恕
For a while in the prison, a doubt crept into me...
在狱中有一刹那 怀疑占据了我的心
No, Thomas. I killed a man
不 托马斯 我杀了一个人
who wanted my honour for pigeon pie. I was...
他要我以荣誉偿还他的鸽子馅饼 我...
There is no past.
没有过去
Only the future.
只有未来
There is something more I must tell you.
还有件事情我要告诉你
I am with child.
我怀孕了
A speedy settlement.
快速解决
I will bring forward new proposals to the Parliament soon.
我将会尽快向议会提交动议
Your Majesty, my heart is filled with joy to hear that promise.
陛下 得到你的承诺 我满心欢喜
But I must tell His Majesty
蒙受陛下厚爱
from the love that I bear Your Majesty,
我还要禀告一事
and ever will, there are some in the army that are put to worry
军队中有些人担心不已
by the many rumours that His Majesty
他们听说了很多传言
yet seeks an intervention from the Scottish force.
说陛下将寻求苏格兰军队的调停
No, no, no, no.
不 不 不 不
No.
不
And that is also a promise from His Majesty?
这也是陛下您的承诺吗?
Of course it is a promise.
当然是承诺
Thomas Rainsborough.
托马斯·雷恩巴勒
What of him, Majesty?
他怎样呢 陛下?
He is a fanatical.
他是个狂人
A Leveller.
一个平等派
Should such a man be in such high command?
能让这样的人担任高层统帅吗?
I would sleep easier in my bed
若他能不再插手我们的事务
if he were removed from our affairs.
我才能早日安寝
Thomas is the best man in England, sire.
托马斯是英格兰最好的人 陛下
And my friend.
是我的挚友
Well, then let any man here tell me a better way.
好 那谁来告诉我别的办法呀
Let any man here tell me any other way
谁来告诉我还有什么办法
this ship can be brought into harbour
能平定纷争
other than to talk to Charles Stuart?
又不必与查尔斯·斯图亚特谈判
He game me solemn undertakings. Promises from his own lips.
他给予我庄重的保证 亲口承诺
Which will prove false as ever before.
跟以前一样 空口无凭
Gentlemen.
先生们
We have Royalist uprisings in south Wales,
王党四起 在南威尔士 约克郡 还有柴郡
in Yorkshire and in Cheshire.
发起暴动
Then let us crush them!
让我们粉碎他们吧
Aye Thomas, we can crush them.
对 托马斯 我们可以粉碎他们
We can spend our lifetimes, and our children's,
我们能以我们和子孙后代的性命
killing and killing again.
不断杀戮
But when the killing stops, where is England?
但当杀戮停止 英格兰何存?
We cannot achieve all, my friends,
我们无法两全齐美的 我的朋友们
but we can achieve... a sufficiency!
我们拥有的已足矣
A sufficiency of Charles Stuart?
查尔斯之流足矣?
A sufficiency of bloated thieves in the Parliament?
议会中狂妄自大 鸡鸣狗盗之徒足矣?
A sufficiency of soldiers who fought for their country,
抑或为国挥洒热血
only to be told they must now starve for the wages promised.
却空守承诺 惨淡贫困之兵士足矣？
I fought not for that sufficiency!
不 我的征战 不是为此等足矣
Hear, hear!
好呀 好呀
Well, what then, Thomas? More death, more destruction, what?
那么将如何 托马斯? 更多死亡和毁灭 还有什么?
We exile Charles Stuart.
我们处决查尔斯·斯图亚特
Let him depart.
除掉他
Let us govern the country through councils elected in the streets
让我们通过普选产生的议会
the guilds, the universities.
行会 大学来统治国家
Elected in the streets? By whom?
普选? 由谁来选?
By all men.
所有人
For I think the poorest he that is in England
因我认为 即使英国最贫苦的人
has a life to live is the greatest he.
能好好过活便相当了不起
No more Parliaments for men with property only.
从此不再有只为有产者而设的议会
We should burn it down.
我们要将它彻底烧毁
Well, then, Thomas...
那么托马斯...
..and all of you, my friends and comrades,
...还有你们 我的朋友以及同伴
I must tell you this.
我只能这样跟你们说
What Colonel Rainsborough urges this council to accept
雷恩巴勒上校催促会议接受的
is a form of government unknown on this Earth,
是世上前所未有的政府形式
and one that will straightway fall into anarchy.
将令我国直接陷入无政府状态
Rather than let this beloved England fall into such misery,
与其让我们深爱的英格兰落得如此悲惨的地步
I tell you now,
我郑重告诉你们
I would pull promises out of Charles Stuart's mouth
我会让查尔斯·斯图亚特亲口
another thousand years.
许下更长久的承诺
Then it's clear, General.
那么达成共识了吧 将军
In this beloved England, one of us will not live.
在这可爱的英格兰 不是你死就是我亡
If you rise up, you will be called mutineers and traitors.
如果你反抗 你们会变成叛徒 卖国贼
Oliver is still the hero.
奥利佛仍然是英雄
Then the regiments must be prepared for this convulsion.
那么军团得为这场动乱做好万全的准备
Reason says we lose all in delay.
经验证明 延误战机会导致落败
Now tell me what your heart says, Edward.
告诉我你的想法 爱德华
I have butchered men.
我屠戮过人命
Here and in Germany.
无论在德国还是这里
But say the word, Colonel,
但只要你一句话 上校
and I will sharpen my blades once again.
我会再擦亮刀锋
This time for justice, not for pay.
这次是并非为报酬 而是为正义
Edward Sexby has nothing to lose on this Earth.
可是上校 爱德华·塞斯比毫无顾虑
Others have.
其他人有
Madam?
夫人?
One man only may unite the Army
在此形势下 只有一个人
in this great matter, Thomas.
能将人们团结起来 托马斯
That man is you.
那个人就是你
Thomas.
托马斯
Charles Stuart has broken his promises.
查尔斯·斯图亚特出尔反尔
Every one of them.
违反了每个承诺
By escaping from Hampton Court.
他逃出汉普顿宫
Gone, it is thought, to the Island of Wight.
不见影踪 人们认为他逃往维特岛
I come to apologise to you...and to all.
我过来向你以及所有人致歉 ...
For that I was foolishly dazzled by him.
我居然如此愚蠢 被他蒙蔽双眼
We will negotiate with this false man no more.
我们不会再和这个伪君子谈判
But, Thomas,
但是 托马斯
there must now be unity amongst us
我们现在必须同心协力
or all will be brought to ruin.
否则将全部灭亡
There are new uprisings today in Essex
今天在埃塞克斯
and in Yorkshire and in Cheshire and in Wales
约克郡 柴郡和威尔士都有新暴动
and in Bristol, too.
布里斯托也有
The country needs its Army now as never before.
国家空前需要军队
What say you?
你意下如何?
When we have done,
当一切完结
will all matters as to how we govern this country
我们治理国家的所有事务
be for discussion?
都会由讨论决定吗?
All matters.
一切事务都会
And will all matters as to land and property be for discussion?
关于土地和财富的所有事务都能讨论吗?
All.
所有
You are needed in Pontefract, Thomas.
潘蒂法克堡需要你 托马斯
A siege such as only you can lift.
只有你才能胜任的攻城战
But I beg of you, make speed.
但我恳请你加快脚步
Our enemies were making ready for this
当我被国王耀眼的光辉蒙蔽时
while I blinked in the sunlight of the king's gaze.
我们的敌人正积极备战
I will go tomorrow.
我明天就出发
Tonight, Thomas.
今晚 托马斯
Tonight must be my wedding night, Oliver.
今晚是我的新婚夜 奥利佛
If my lady will marry a soldier that will be gone in the morning?
如果我的夫人愿嫁给一个明天就要出征的战士
She will.
她愿意
May God grant you a long life together.
愿上帝庇佑你们百年好合
I must go to Wales, a thing I never thought to do.
我要前往威尔士 从未想过要做这样的事
Fare you well.
一路走好
Will you not offer me a wedding gift, General?
你不给我一份结婚礼物吗 将军?
If it can be done.
假如能做到的话
Let John Lilburne go free.
让约翰·李尔本无罪开释
Overthrow Parliament's warrant.
推翻议会的命令
It is done, madam.
一定办到 夫人
By authority of the Army.
以军队的权力
You will not make me a wife for one night, I hope?
你该不会只让我做一夜妻子吧?
I must disappoint you, Edward.
我要令你失望了 爱德华
No fight for you.
你不能跟我出征
Till I return, guard this woman with your life.
在我归来之前 请你以生命守护这位夫人
Why do you sleep on straw still, Sexby?
你为什么还睡在稻草堆里 塞斯比?
I wish you were by Thomas' side in Yorkshire.
我希望你在约克郡 在托马斯身旁
I wish it, too.
是啊 我也希望如此
He is the best man I ever met.
他是我见过最好的人
Sexby, do you ever think of those times in Wytham Woods?
塞斯比 你回想过威萨姆森林里的事吗?
I have never been in Wytham Woods, my lady.
我从未去过威萨姆森林 我的夫人
Except once.
除了一次
To swim one day when I was hot.
有一天我热的时候去游过泳
We come with a message from General Cromwell.
给克伦威尔将军的信
When you were the god of battles,
当你是战场的上帝时
there was ever a sign of your blessing on me.
你一直庇护着我
Now when you rest upon my shoulders, my sight is dim.
现在当你在我肩头歇息 我的视线变得模糊
I think I see the road...
我想我看到路在何方
..and yet I fear to tread it.
...却害怕踏上征途
I know the man I must strike down
我知道我必须击败谁
and yet I fear the blood that will be shed thereafter.
却害怕从此以后 鲜血将四处流淌
The fight...
战斗...
Take men to the Island and arrest Charles Stuart.
带人前往岛屿 逮捕查尔斯·斯图亚特
He will be charged with making unlawful war on England.
他将被指控在英国发动非法战争
Let others stand ready to enter the Parliament.
让其他人准备好进入议会
The time has come.
时候到了
Husband.
夫君
Yes?
怎么了?
There will be a life for us, will there not?
我们会有新的生活 是吗?
One day the argument will be over.
总有一天纷争会结束
There is a life to come.
新生活会来临的
Arrest her.
逮捕她
You shall not touch her!
你不可以碰她
Sexby, desist.
塞斯比 停手
What does it matter now? Let them hang me.
现在又有什么关系呢? 让他们吊死我吧